A Guide to the Papers of the Melcher Family, 1785-1987
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Melcher Family 1785-1987
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11082-a,-b
10,500 items
The Melcher Family Papers consist of personal and professional correspondence, diaries, journals, photographs, research, taped material, and writings of Daniel Melcher, Frederic Gershom Melcher, and Marguerite Fellows Melcher.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The papers were a gift from Margaret S. Melcher and Frederic G. Melcher, 1995 June 6 and July 17.
Scope and Content Information
Papers of Daniel Melcher consist of personal and professional correspondence; printed material on publishing and printing; drafting instruments; and photographs and slides of the Melchers and others, and their travels; letters to his parents from the Netherlands, Germany, and England, and from Harvard University; genealogical material of the Melcher, Atkins, Fellows, Flagg and related families, some dating to the 18th century, and personal mementos.
In addition there is a copy of Melcher's thesis Trade-Unionism as a factor in the decline of New York City book printing industry. There are also copies of the news bulletin Schools at War, 1942-1946 and related photographs; IAHP instruction kits; honorary memberships and recognitions for Daniel Melcher and Frederic G. Melcher; cassettes; memorabilia; and artwork, including sketch of Robert Frost.
Daniel Melcher's papers also contain cassette tapes of the Newbery and Caldecott acceptance speeches by Joan W. Blos, Marcia Brown, Leo and Diane Dillon, Paul Goble, Elizabeth Orton Jones, Robert Lawson, Patricia MacLachlan, Ellen Raskin, Peter Spier, Mildred D. Taylor, Chris Van Allsburg, Cynthia Voight, and Nancy Willard, as well as a tape of music inspired by the book Ben's Trumpet.
Papers of Frederic Gershom Melcher contain diaries, 1897-1898; a Japanese travel journal, 1947; photographs and other material regarding Robert Frost; correspondence including letters from Willa Cather, Mary Ellen Chase, Melvil Dewey, Albert Einstein, Dwight Eisenhower, Langston Hughes, and John Hall Wheelock; papers on printing and bookselling, the Frederic G. Melcher Book Award, the Frederick G. Melcher Scholarship, Wellfleet, Mass., and Melcher's library. There are also awards, honors and mementos.
Frederic G. Melcher's papers also contain correspondence with Frederic and Bertha Goudy and the Village Press, Bruce Rogers, Daniel Berkeley Updike and The Merrymount Press; and letters, 1963, regarding the death of F. G. Melcher.
Papers of Marguerite Fellows Melcher consist of her correspondence, research, and writings. Included are manuscripts of her plays, poems, stories and other writings; material on the New Jersey League of Women Voters; and research on the Shakers.
Her papers also contain an audiotape on Shaker history.
Arrangement
Alphabetically by subject.
Contents List
- Papers of Frederic Gershom Melcher re Books and Publishing (Box 1-5)
  - Anniversary Dinner for Frederic G. Melcher to Celebrate Fifty Years in the Book Trade May-Sept. 1945, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Awards given to Frederic G. Melcher 1924-1962, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Book Prices and related 1928-1937 (Box 1)
  - Books in Schools 1939-1963 (Box 1)
  - Bookseller's Education and Reading 1940-1941 (Box 1)
  - Bookselling in Indiana [1918] (Box 1)
  - Boston Bookselling at the Turn of the Century 1951-1956 (Box 1)
  - Britain and Books 1945 (Box 1)
  - Children's Books and Book Week 1928-1963 (Box 1)
  - Children's Books Awards 1942-1964 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence of Frederic G. Melcher 1914-1963 (Box 2)
  - Editorials in Publishers' Weekly by Frederic G. Melcher 1944-1947 (Box 2)
  - Freedom to Read/Censorship 1944-1948 (Box 2)
  - Frederic G. Melcher Book Award 1962-1981, 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Frederic G. Melcher Library, Police Athletic League's Wynn Center, Brooklyn 1964-1968 (Box 2)
  - Frederic G. Melcher Literary Collection 1980 (Box 2)
  - Frederic G. Melcher Scholarship 1964-1968, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Frederic G. Melcher Scholarship Fund Campaign 1963-1966, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Gifts of Manuscripts and Books to Institutions 1937-1963 (Box 3)
  - Frederic W. and Bertha M. Goudy, The Village Press 1922-1938, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Graphic Arts 1945-1960 (Box 3)
  - International Publishers Congress 1936 (Box 4)
  - Librarians and the Book Trade 1935-1962 (Box 4)
  - Library of Books about Books 1956-1963 (Box 4)
  - Memoirs of Frederic G. Melcher 1944-1960 (Box 4)
  - Memorabilia re Frederic G. Melcher 1940-1967, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Notes on Publishers kept by Frederic G. Melcher 1933-1945 (Box 4)
  - Papers re Frederic G. Melcher 1919-1964 (Box 4)
  - Poets and Poetry 1957-1958 (Box 4)
  - Printers and Printing 1927-1950 (Box 4)
  - R.R. Bowker Company 1922-1947 (Box 4)
  - Bruce Rogers: Catalogs and Pamphlets re his works 1920-1955, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Bruce Rogers: Catalogs and Pamphlets re his works, printed by William Edwin Rudge 1925-1942 (Box 4)
  - Bruce Rogers: Catalogs and Pamplets re his works, printedby S.R. Shapiro 1954-1956 (Box 4)
  - Bruce Rogers: Correspondence and Memorabilia 1928-1955 (Box 4)
  - UNESCO and contacts between American book trade and that of other countries 1945-1962 (Box 5)
  - Daniel Berkeley Updike, The Merrymount Press 1919-1929 (Box 5)
  - Daniel Berkeley Updike, the Merrymount Press - Greetings for the New Year to the Friends of the Merrymount Press 1912-1948 (Box 5)
  - Hendrik Willem van Loon 1927-1939 (Box 5)
  - Writings by Frederic G. Melcher 1918-1962, 2 folders (Box 5)
- Topical Papers of Frederic Gershom Melcher (Box 5-7)
  - Condolences on death of Frederic Gershom Melcher 1963, 5 folders (Box 5)
  - Condolences on death of Frederic Gershom to Marguerite Fellows Melcher 1963 (Box 6)
  - Diaries kept by Frederic G. Melcher 1897-1898 (Box 6)
  - Eightieth Birthday Celebration 1959 (Box 1959)
  - Robert Frost: Photographs and Printed 1914-1963 (Box 6)
  - Household Account 1918-1922 (Box 6)
  - Robert Frost: articles re 1920-1936 (Box 6)
  - Legal Papers of Frederic G. Melcher 1962-1963 (Box 6)
  - Obituaries and Tributes for Frederic G. Melcher 1963-1964 (Box 6)
  - Personal Correspondence of Frederic G. Melcher 1934-1956 (Box 6)
  - Photographs and Identification Certificates 1930s-1940s, n.d. (Box 6)
  - Travel Journal of Trip to Japan kept by Frederic G. Melcher 1947 Mar-Apr (Box 6)
  - V.I.P. Correspondence of Frederic G. Melcher [Willa Cather, Mary Ellen Chase, Melvil Dewey, Dwight David Eisenhower, Albert Einstein, Langston Hughes, and John Hall Wheelock] 1918-1953 (Box 6)
  - Wellfleet, Massachusetts 1937-1963, 4 folders (Box 7)
- Bound Volumes of Frederic Gershom Melcher (Box 7)
  - Our Book. We children of Watchung dedicate this book to our dear friend, Mr. Melcher, autograph poems and sketches, authored by different students but written in one hand 1936 (Box 7)
  - Frederic G. Melcher: Friendly Reminscences of a Half Century Among Books & Bookmen, along with autographs of well-wishers (transferred to Rare Books) 1945 (Box 7)
  - Melcher of Montclair 1945, scrapbook including list of contributors and quotes concerning Frederic G. Melcher 1945 (Box 7)
  - To Frederic G. Melcher from the Montclair Education Association, autograph book with contributions from well-wishers 1946 (Box 7)
  - PW--ANNoLXXVo--FGM, bound copy of Publishers' Weekly, January 18, 1947, on the occasion of its seventy-fifth anniversary, signed by well-wishers 1947 (Box 7)
- Correspondence and Papers of Marguerite Fellows Melcher (Box 8-12)
  - Address Book of Marguerite F. Melcher 1950s-1960s (Box 8)
  - Central America Photographs n.d. (Box 8)
  - Christmas Cards sent by Marguerite and Frederic G. Melcher 1917, 1934-1967, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Condolences on death of Charity (Melcher) Travis 1967 (Box 8)
  - Condolences on death of Marguerite (Fellows) Melcher 1969-1970, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Correspondence of Marguerite (Fellows) Melcher 1895-1964, n.d. (Box 9)
  - Frederic G. Melcher to Marguerite F. Melcher 1947,1956 (Box 9)
  - "Leaguesboro-on-the-Air," New Jersey League of Women Voters 1940s, 4 folders (Box 9)
  - Literary Correspondence and Papers 1927-1941, 6 folders (Box 9)
  - Literary Correspondence and Papers 1942-1972, 10 folders (Box 10)
  - Literary Correspondence and Papers re Making Plays from Stories Offstage, with reprint of book 1938,1967 (Box 10)
  - Literary Correspondence and Papers re The Shaker Adventure1938-1942, 1959 (Box 11)
  - Literary Reviews for The Shaker Adventure 1941-1946 (Box 11)
  - The Log of the "Sea-Legs," with brief log of the "Molly Gull" 1928-1930 (Box 11)
  - Photographs 1960s (Box 11)
  - Poems, Essays, and Notes kept by Marguerite F. Melcher 1950s, n.d. (Box 11)
  - The Shakers: Correspondence 1935-1968, n.d., 3 folders (Box 11)
  - The Shakers: Notes kept by Marguerite F. Melcher 1950-1959, n.d. (Box 11)
  - The Shakers: Photographs and Postcards 1900s-1960s (Box 11)
  - The Shakers: Printed Articles 1837, 1933-1969, n.d., 2 folders (Box 11)
  - The Shakers: Printed Brochures and Bulletins 1907-1969, n.d., 3 folders (Box 12)
  - The Shakers: Shaker Heights Then and Now1938 (Box 12)
- Plays by Marguerite Fellows Melcher (Box 12-18)
  - "Before and After," a play in two scenes, with autograph revisions, 4 copies n.d. (Box 12)
  - "Curtains," a play in one act n.d., 7 copies (Box 12)
  - "Commencement," a play in one act n.d. (Box 12)
  - "He Went Sailing," a play in three acts, 4 versions 1951, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - "Just Outside," a play in one act n.d. (Box 13)
  - "Land Where," a tragedy in three acts, 4 versions [1952], 2 folders (Box 13)
  - "Man Higher Up," a melodrama in three acts, 2 versions 1953 (Box 13)
  - "Museum Piece," a play in three acts, with autograph revisions n.d. (Box 13)
  - "Museum Piece," or "The Haunted Tapestry," a story n.d. (Box 13)
  - "New Deal," a play in one act n.d. (Box 13)
  - "Not a Selfish Bone," a one-act play, 2 versions n.d. (Box 13)
  - "Not Bread Alone" or "They Also Serve," a comedy in three acts n.d. (Box 13)
  - "Office Discard," a play in one act n.d. (Box 13)
  - "Our Flag is Still There," 4 versions, printed 1941 (Box 13)
  - "The Pink Slip," a play in two acts, 2 versions n.d. (Box 14)
  - "The Princess who would not Smile," a play in one act 1947 (Box 14)
  - "Prisoners of Hope," dramatization in five episodes, 3 versions n.d. (Box 14)
  - "Private Lesson," a comedy in one act n.d. (Box 14)
  - "Private Lesson," a comedy in one act, with autograph revisions n.d. (Box 14)
  - "Private Practise," a comedy in three acts n.d. (Box 14)
  - "Private Practise," a comedy in three acts, 2 versions n.d. (Box 14)
  - "Provincetown," a play in five acts, 1st version and synopsis n.d. (Box 14)
  - "P'Town," a play in two acts, old version n.d. (Box 14)
  - "P'Town," a play in three acts n.d. (Box 14)
  - "P'Town," a play, 3 versions n.d. (Box 14)
  - "Pulitzer Prize," a play in one act, 5 versions n.d. (Box 15)
  - "Rose in the Wilderness," acting version 1949 (Box 15)
  - "Rose in the Wilderness," a play about the Shakers in New Hampshire n.d. (Box 15)
  - "Rose in the Wilderness," a play in three acts n.d. (Box 15)
  - "Rose in the Wilderness," a play in three acts with prologue and epilogue 1935 (Box 15)
  - "Rose in the Wilderness," a play in three acts with prologue and epilogue n.d., 3 folders (Box 15)
  - "Rose in the Wilderness," synopsis, theme, and related n.d. (Box 15)
  - "Second Answer," a play in three acts n.d. (Box 16)
  - "60 Cycle Hum," a three-act play, and accompanying notes 1933-1940 (Box 16)
  - "60 Cycle Hum," a comedy in three acts, 2nd version 1940 (Box 16)
  - "60 Cycle Hum," a comedy in three acts, with few autograph revisions, 2nd version and revision 1940,1942 (Box 16)
  - "60 Cycle Hum," a comedy in three acts, with few autograph revisions, 3rd revision and carbon 1943 Jun, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - "Some One to Talk to," a one-act play n.d. (Box 16)
  - "Some One to Talk to," a one-act play, with autograph revisions, 6 copies n.d. (Box 16)
  - "Stephen," a play in one act, with few autograph revisions, 2 copies n.d. (Box 16)
  - "Steps Unto Heaven/The World is Good," a one-act play, written for the centenary celebration of the Church at Enfield Center 1936 (Box 16)
  - "Tam Glen," a melodrama in three acts, carbon 1961 (Box 16)
  - "Tam Glen," a melodrama in three acts [1961], 2 folders (Box 17)
  - "Tax Exempt," a play in one act n.d. (Box 17)
  - "Tax Exempt," a play in one act, with few autograph revisions n.d. (Box 17)
  - "They Also Serve/Super-Market," a comedy in three acts n.d. (Box 17)
  - "Tune in to Now" (or "Sixty Cycle Hum"), a comedy in three acts n.d., 2 folders (Box 17)
  - "The Unicorn," a play in two acts [1949] (Box 17)
  - "The Unicorn," a play in two acts, with few autograph revisions [1949] (Box 17)
  - "The Unicorn," a play in three acts, with heavy autograph revisions [1949] (Box 17)
  - "The Unicorn," a play in three acts, with few autograph revisions [1949] (Box 17)
  - "The Unicorn," a play in three acts, with heavy autograph revisions, revised 1950,1951 (Box 17)
  - "We Hold These Truths," a play in one act 1946 (Box 18)
  - "What Child is This?" a Christmas play in one act, with few autograph revisions, 4 copies n.d. (Box 18)
  - "What More do you Want?" a play in one act 1946 (Box 18)
  - "Why Mothers Leave Home," a play in one act n.d. (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous Plays 1946, n.d. (Box 18)
  - Papers and Notes re Plays 1954-1964, n.d. (Box 18)
  - Photographs of "Rose in the Wilderness" [1948] (Box 18)
  - Photographs of ["Rose in the Wilderness"] n.d. (Box 18)
  - Synopses and Lists of Plays n.d. (Box 18)
  - Unidentified Plays n.d. (Box 18)
- Poems and Stories by Marguerite Fellows Melcher (Box 18-20)
  - Poems 1926-1948, n.d., 2 folders (Box 18)
  - "Back Pay" n.d. (Box 19)
  - "The Quest of the Birch-Maiden" n.d. (Box 19)
  - "The Rose Computer" 1966-1967 (Box 19)
  - "The Rose Computer" 1972 (Box 19)
  - "Search for the Dragon," a story, with autograph revisions, 2 copies n.d. (Box 19)
  - "West Content," a story, with few autograph revisions n.d., 2 folders (Box 19)
  - Short Stories n.d., 2 folders (Box 19)
  - Short Stories n.d., 7 folders (Box 20)
  - Stories for Children 1925-1935 (Box 20)
  - Verses and Sketches 1927-1965, n.d. (Box 20)
  - Writings n.d. (Box 20)
- Correspondence and Papers of Daniel Melcher (Box 21-26)
  - Daniel Melcher to his family, chiefly from Harvard University 1928-1934, 2 folders (Box 21)
  - Daniel Melcher to his family, while travelling in Europe 1932 Jun-Aug (Box 21)
  - Charlotte S. Beal 1931-1954 (Box 21)
  - Harvard College Academic Reports and Senior Spread Programs; and, Anniversary Reports 1931-1934,1959,1974 (Box 21)
  - Mabel F. Melcher 1936-1961, [1970] (Box 21)
  - Montclair High School English Essays 1930-1931, 2 folders (Box 21)
  - "Mother's Book" kept by Marguerite F. Melcher on first years of Daniel, Nancy and Charity 1912-1921 (Box 21)
  - Newbery-Caldecott Award 1965-1973, 3 folders (Box 21)
  - Newbery-Caldecott Award 1974-1984, 2 folders (Box 22)
  - Notebook containg wine bottle labels and comments on wine kept by Daniel Melcher 1959-1962,1980 (Box 22)
  - Personal Correspondence and Papers 1956-1987, 3 folders (Box 22)
  - Photographs: Europe - Holland and Germany 1932 Jun-Aug (Box 22)
  - Photographs: Glen Echo 1974-1977, 2 folders (Box 22)
  - Photographs: Galapagos 1972, 3 folders (Box 23)
  - Photographs: Glen Echo 1978-1979, n.d., 2 folders (Box 23)
  - Photographs: Institutes for the Achievement of Human Potential--The Better Baby Press 1984 (Box 23)
  - Photographs: Daniel Melcher and others 1914-1967, n.d. (Box 23)
  - Photographs: Daniel and Margaret (Saul) Melcher and others 1957-1976, n.d. (Box 23)
  - Photographs: Mexico 1969 (1970) (Box 23)
  - Photographs: Midwest - Arizona & Utah 1969, 2 folders (Box 24)
  - Photographs: Midwest - Arizona, Nevada & California 1969 (Box 24)
  - Photographs: Midwest 1969 (Box 24)
  - Photographs: Miscellaneous 1969-1974, n.d. (Box 24)
  - Photographs: Puerto Rico 1970 (Box 24)
  - Photographs: Rumania n.d. (Box 24)
  - Photographs: War Bond Programs/War Finance Division/Education Section - Schools-at-War 1944-1946, 2 folders (Box 24)
  - Photographic Slides: Great Britain, Spain, Netherlands, France, Mexico, Puerto Rico, Midwest America, and other places in Europe and the United States. Persons include Daniel Melcher, Peggy (Zimmerman) Melcher, Margaret (Saul) Melcher, Frederic G. Melcher II, and others. Some slides are identified. 1940s-1970s, 34 sheets, ca. 600 slides (Box 25)
  - Political Issues 1963-1983 (Box 26)
  - Property: Montclair--45 Dodd Street 1947-1963 (Box 26)
  - Thesis "Trade-Unionism as a Factor in the Decline of New York City Book Printing Industry" 1934 (Box 26)
- Original and Biographical/Genealogical Information (Box 26-28)
  - Biographical Data on Daniel Melcher (b. 1799) and related Genealogical Data on Flagg-Melcher line, compiled by Dorothy M. Vaughan 1949-1954 (Box 26)
  - Biographical Data on John Melcher (b. 1759) with information on his printing career 1940, 1950-1952 (Box 26)
  - Day Book of Daniel Melcher (b. 1799) Exeter, New Hampshire 1820-1823 (Box 26)
  - Financial and Legal Papers of the Melcher family and related 1785-1862 (Box 26)
  - Genealogical Data on the Atkins and related Dodge and Gibbs families n.d. (Box 26)
  - Genealogical Data on the Fellows and related Johnson and Smith families 1973, n.d. (Box 26)
  - Genealogical Data on the Melcher and related Fellows and Flagg families 1934-1981 (Box 26)
  - Montclair High School Yearbook Amphitheatre1930 (Box 27)
  - The Harvard Freshman Red Book 1934 (Box 27)
  - Memorabilia: Printer's instruments, including proportional dividers, radiograph technical fountain pen, and slide rule. Miscellaneous memorabilia including medal from Rio de Janeiro and [Daniel Melcher's] baby shoes. n.d. (Box 28)
- Harvard Class Album 1934, Oversize bound volume
- Schools at War, 1942-1946: Bound copies of the war savings news bulletin for teachers 1942-1946, Oversize bound volume
- Papers of Frederic Gershom Melcher re Books and Publishing (Box S-53)
  - Awards: Appointment of Frederic G. Melcher as representative to the Fifty-Eighth Annual Conference of the American Library Association 1936 (Box S-53)
  - Frederick W. Goudy, The Village Press n.d. (Box S-53)
  - Daniel Berkeley Updike, The Merrymount Press n.d. (Box S-53)
- Topical Papers of Frederic Gershom Melcher (Box S-53)
  - Season's Greetings cards 1961, n.d. (Box S-53)
- Plays by Marguerite Fellows Melcher (Box S-53)
  - "Unicorn," poster for play presented by the Columbia Theater Associates [1949] (Box S-53)
- Papers of Daniel Melcher (Box S-53)
  - Harvard University Diploma for Daniel Melcher 1934 (Box S-53)
  - Photographs: World War II - home life ca. 1942-1944 (Box S-53)
- Photograph of the Frederic G. Melcher Anniversary Dinner to Celebrate 50 Years in Book Trade, 1895-1945 1945 May (Box M-26)
- Newbery-Caldecott Medal Acceptance Speeches: Ashanti to Zulu: African Traditions, Leo and Diane Dillon (Caldecott); Roll of Thunder, Hear My Cry, Mildred D. Taylor (Newbery) 1977 (Othertype Audiocassette 0029)
- Newbery-Caldecott Medal Acceptance Speeches: Noah's Ark, Peter Spier (Caldecott); Bridge to Terabithia, Katherine Paterson (Newbery) 1978 (Othertype Audiocassette 0030)
- Newbery-Caldecott Medal Acceptance Speeches: The Westing Game, Ellen Raskin (Newbery); The Girl Who Loved Wild Horses, Paul Goble (Caldecott) 1979 (Othertype Audiocassette 0031)
- Newbery-Caldecott Medal Acceptance Speeches: A Gathering of Day, Joan W. Blos (Newbery); Rabbit Hill, Robert Lawson, 1945 (Newbery); Prayer for a Child, Elizabeth Orton Jones, 1945 1980 (Othertype Audiocassette 0032)
- Newbery-Caldecott Medal Acceptance Speeches: A Visit to William Blake's Inn, Nancy Willard (Newbery); Jumanji, Chris Van Allsburg (Caldecott) 1982 (Othertype Audiocassette 0033)
- Newbery-Caldecott Medal Acceptance Speeches: Shadow, Marcia Brown (Caldecott); Dicey's Song, Cynthia Voigt 1983 (Othertype Audiocassette 0034)
- Newbery-Caldecott Medal Acceptance Speeches: The Polar Express, Chris Van Allsburg (Caldecott); Sarah, Plain and Tall, Patricia MacLachlan 1986 (Othertype Audiocassette 0035)
- Music inspired by the Caldecott Honor Book and Filmstrip Ben's Trumpet by Rachel Isadora 1980 (Othertype Audiocassette 0036)
- Shakers History n.d., magnetic recording tape--1/4" x 1200 ft. (Othertype Audiotape 0005)
- The double duty dollar, 16 mm, b&w, sound (Reel 0295)
  Produced by the War Finance Department of the United States Treasury.
- Public relations planner presents opportunities unlimited, 16mm, color, sound (Reel 0296)
- The brotherhood of man, 16mm, color, sound (Reel 0297)
  Based on a pamphlet by Ruth Benedict and Gene Weltfish and published by the Public Affairs Committee of the UAW-CIO.
- Untitled home movie, 16mm, color, no sound (Reel 0298)